Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge

May 17, 2015

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science May 2011 - Dec 2014 Purdue University, USA

Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science *Aug 2008 – May 2011* Purdue University, USA GPA: 3.94/4

Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering Aug 2004 - May 2008 PSG College of Technology GPA: 9.55/10 Anna University, India

Experience

Research Associate, University of Cambridge

Dec 2014 - present Advisor: Anil Madhavapeddy Cambridge, UK

Developing Multicore OCaml under the OCaml Labs initiative in the Computer Laboratory.

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Aug 2008 - Dec 2014 Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, USA Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Aug 2012 - Dec 2012 Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) Aug 2011 – Dec 2011

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Feb 2012 - May 2012 Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D)

May 2010 - Aug 2010 Advisor: Daniel Waddington San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language - a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)

Dec 2007 - Apr 2008 Advisor: Sankar Chnab Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML Nov 2014 J2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 - 674 **Efficient Sessions** Feb 2013 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster J1 Science of Computer Programming (SCP), 78(2): 147 – 167 Invited paper Conference Publications **Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores** Jun 2015 **C7** KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Rx-CML:** A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 **C6** KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL) A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan C5 Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award **Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness** Jun 2012 C4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM) **Composable Asynchronous Events** Jun 2011 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan **C**3 International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) **Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction** June 2010 C2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION) **Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication** Sep 2009 C1 Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP) Workshop Publications Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud Sep 2013 W4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Apr 2011 W3 Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan

The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Sep 2010 Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek W2 ML Workshop **Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads** Jan 2010 W1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP) Technical Reports and Drafts **Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell** Dec 2014 T2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones Under consideration for Journal of Functional Programming (JFP) **Featherweight Threads for Communication** Nov 2011 T1 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report - TR-11-018 Talks **Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems** Dec 2014 PhD Defense Purdue University Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming Mar 2014 Invited Lecture Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 PADL 2014 San Diego, CA Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud Sep 2013 ML Workshop 2013 Boston, MA A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 **MARC 2012 RWTH Aachen** Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness ISMM 2012, Beijing Jun 2012 Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge May 2012 Lightweight Concurrency in GHC May 2012 Wrestling Wednesdays Microsoft Research, Cambridge **Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction** Jun 2012 **COORDINATION 2012** CWI Amsterdam Professional Service

- Program Committee member: SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015.
- Reviewer: POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellow, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).

- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013.